given two positive real numbers X and Y
Place lines of length X and Y side by
side to form the diameter of a circle
whose radius is X Plus y over two
at the intersection point of the two
lines create a half chord to the circle
of length Z the triangle formed here
must be a right triangle by thales
triangle theorem and so these two
subtriangles must be similar this means
that Z over X has to be equal to Y over
Z and we can simplify this to see that Z
squared equals x times y so that the
length of Z is equal to the square root
of x times y
notice that no matter the lengths of X
and Y this half chord is always less
than or equal to the radius therefore we
see that the square root of x times Y is
less than or equal to the quantity X
Plus y over 2. the only way that these
two quantities are equal is if x equals
y
this is known as the arithmetic mean
geometric mean inequality